This is poison.
これは毒薬よ
I had someone test it.
人に試させたわ
It won't take effect until tomorrow.
毒が回るのは明日よ
It will be painless.
苦痛は一切ないわ
To die tomorrow?
明日死ぬだと
What's the use
余の命を
of keeping me alive
明日に延ばして
until tomorrow?
何の得がある
Xiao Wuyi has agreed to cooperate with me.
蕭無衣は協力すると約束したわ
But now,
でも今
there's still one thing missing—
一つ足りないものがある
a pledge of allegiance.
投名状よ
So you want to use my life
私の命で
to announce Xiao Wuyi's betrayal.
蕭無衣の裏切りを知らしめるの
Lejun!
楽君
Have you lost your mind?
気は確かか
This is a deadly poison!
死に至る毒だぞ
Wasn't it you who told me to drink it?
飲めと言ったのはそなたでは
But
違う
I could have found a way
手立てはある
to keep you alive.
生かしてやる
Didn't it ever occur to you
一度たりとも余に
to beg me just once?
命乞いをしようとは思わなかったのか
But I no longer wish to live.
でも もう生きたくないの
Mulian Yu.
穆連余
What are you still pretending for?
今さら何を演じているの
Did you bring poison here today
まさか今日 毒薬を持ってきたのは
just to hear me beg for mercy?
私が命乞いするのを聞くためだとでも
Three years.
三年だ
You've been by my side for 3 years.
余のそばにいた三年の間
Three years of marriage between us—
三年の夫婦の情け
all my indulgence toward you,
そなたを甘やかし
all the affection I showed you—
寵愛したというのに
did none of it earn even a shred of your genuine affection?
一片の真心すら得られなかったというのか
No.
ないわ
Our homelands are enemies.
そなたと私の母国は敵同士
All my blood relatives
私の血縁は皆
were killed by you Northern Qin people.
そなたたち北秦の者に殺された
Our families have been sworn enemies for generations.
私たちは代々の仇敵
How could there be any genuine affection between us?
真心などありえない
Mulian Yu.
穆連余
Can you promise me one thing?
一つだけ約束してくれない
If one day you win
もし あなたが勝ち
and lead your army to attack Jiankang,
大軍を率いて剣慷に攻め入ったなら
can you please
兄上を見逃し
spare my brother's life?
命だけは助けてほしい
He's the only family
あの方は この世でただ一人の
I have left in this world.
私の身内なの
Ridiculous.
滑稽だ
Absolutely ridiculous.
実に滑稽だな
If Heaven favors me
天が余に味方し
and that day truly comes.
その日が来たならば
I'll kill him with my own hands.
この手で奴を殺してやる
That way, you two can be reunited sooner,
早くお前たちを再会させてやろう
and it won't have been in vain that you submitted yourself to the enemy,
奴のために仇敵に身を寄せ
exhausting your wits
心血を注ぎ
and plotting your entire life for his sake.
一生を懸けた甲斐もあろう
Mulian Yu!
穆連余
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
I've schemed against you once again.
またあなたを謀ってしまった
If there is a next life,
来世があるなら
may we meet again with different identities.
違う身分で巡り会いましょう
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
If you truly have faith in him,
真に彼を信じるならば
please allow him
彼を真の
to stand before you as a true rival.
好敵手と認めてやってくれ
Lejun.
楽君
Mao.
兄上
I came too late.
兄上が遅くなったぞ
You finally came to pick me up.
やっと迎えに来てくれたのね
Lejun.
楽君
I... I want to go home.
私… 帰りたい
Lejun... Lejun...
楽君 楽君
♪ If fate is fragile, what is right or wrong? ♪
帰ろう
Lejun!
楽君
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Mao, I'm so tired.
兄上… とても疲れました
The Eagle King has treated me very well.
鷹王は私によくしてくださいました
He knew all along that I was a spy,
私が密偵だととっくにご存じで
yet he still sincerely wanted to give me a peaceful life for the years I had left.
それでも私の穏やかな余生を心から願ってくださったのです
But I could never give him my genuine affection.
なのに私は真心で応えられませんでした
With the deep-seated hatred between our Prince Qi's household and him,
岐王府への深い恨み
I could neither love him nor hate him.
愛すことも憎むこともできず
Once our two nations go to war,
ひとたび両国が戦となれば
it's bound to be a fight where one side must die.
あなたが死ぬか 私が死ぬかです
Today, I'm returning those 3 stolen years
盗んだこの３年を
to Jiayu all at once.
今日まとめて嘉魚にお返しします
With my death,
私の命と引き換えに
Xiao Wuyi should be able to gain
蕭無衣は得られるはず
the trust of Northern Qin.
北秦の信頼を
Perhaps this can finally atone
これで
for the sins I committed at Lingfeng Fort.
崔郡で犯した罪も償えたでしょうか
Please allow me to use this life of mine
どうかこの命で
to finally usher in the beginning of
兄上の覇業の
your imperial legacy, Mao.
序幕を開かせてください
Mao.
兄上
Forgive me.
お許しください
I want to rest now.
もう休みたいのです
Retreat!
撤退
What if I don't want to be the wife of the infamous Demon Xiao,
もし私が蕭という大魔王の妻ではなく
but the wife of a hero?
英雄の妻になりたいと言ったら
I want you to live a long life,
長生きしてほしいの
to live in peace,
穏やかに暮らして
to leave behind an honorable name,
清廉な家名を伝え
and to be remembered by all.
天下に名を轟かせて
You are making things difficult for me.
無茶を言う
That's right.
ええ
I insist on doing so.
あえて無茶を言うわ
Will you listen to me?
聞いてくれるの
On the day of the competition,
試合の日
I took a liking to you.
あなたに一目ぼれした
My desire to marry you comes from my heart.
あなたを娶ろうとしたのは私の私心
It was never an act.
偽りではなかった
It's no coincidence.
奇遇ですね
I came here specifically to find you.
あなたを探しに来たところです
♪ If I could lay my heart bare and cross ♪
美人が懐に飛び込んでくるのを
how could I possibly refuse?
この私が断れましょうか
I've brought your two guards
そなたの護衛２人を
back to you.
連れ戻しておいたぞ
Aren't you worried I'll run away?
私が逃げると思わないの
Yesterday,
昨日
in front of the two armies,
両軍の目の前で
you killed Li Lejun in front of everyone,
李楽君を殺し
proving your determination.
自らの覚悟を証明した
With this pledge of loyalty,
その忠誠心があれば
what more could I possibly worry about?
案ずることは何もない
What?
どうした
You want to kill me?
私を殺す気か
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
You've actually chosen to side with the Northern Qin bandits.
よくも北秦の賊徒と手を組んだな
Are you still worthy of the title of Crown Prince Wenxi?
文熹太子（ぶんき）の名に
How can you face the brothers of the Beifu Army?
北府の仲間たちに顔向けできるのか
I, Xiao Wuyi, have never feared what others say.
この蕭無衣 人言を恐れたことはない
If I hadn't done this,
私がこうしなければ
would you
お前たちや
and those people of Southern Ye trapped in that sheep pen
羊の囲いの中にいる南鄴の民に
still have a chance to survive?
生きる道があったか
Li Mao slaughtered my entire family
李茂は我が一族を皆殺しにし
and seized control of the Beifu Army from me.
北府軍の兵権を奪った
Now, driven by greed for glory, he's rushing headlong into danger,
今また手柄を焦り
poised to send our Beifu soldiers
我が北府の兄弟たちを
straight under the blades and axes of the Northern Qin Army.
北秦の刃の前に差し出そうとしている
When that happens, forget about the Northern Expedition—
その時になれば北伐どころか
even the entire Northern Border will fall.
北境全土が陥落する
Soon enough, you'll find out
お前たちもすぐに分かるはずだ
who's right and who's wrong.
どちらが正しく どちらが間違っているか
My deal with the Eagle King
私が鷹王と取引したのは
is nothing more than a way to reclaim
元々 私のものだった物を
what originally belonged to me.
取り戻すためだ
Whether to stay... Or to leave,
去るか残るか
it's up to you.
お前たちが決めろ
My parents were both killed by the people of Northern Qin.
私の両親は北秦の者に殺された
I swear I'll never ally myself with these bandits in this lifetime.
この生涯 賊徒とは決して与せぬと誓ったのだ
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
you're not worthy of the title of Crown Prince Wenxi.
お前は文熹太子（ぶんき）の名にふさわしくない
Please forgive us, Your Highness.
世子様、お許しを
Whether they live or die,
あの者たちの生死は
Young Lord Xiao, it's your call.
蕭世子様がご決断ください
They're just 2 stray dogs.
ただの二匹の負け犬です
Let them get lost.
とっとと追い払いなさい
Don't look back.
振り返るな
The more isolated His Highness is,
世子様が孤立すればするほど
the more the Eagle King will trust him.
鷹王は世子様を信じるのです
Lejun wanted to completely sever
楽君は完全に断ち切るつもりなのだな
the bond between you and Xiao Wuyi.
そなたと蕭無衣との絆を
Just like how it was back then
あの時のように
with my mother's death.
俺の母上の死が原因で
No matter how many reasons I came up with,
だから俺がいくら理由を考え
or how many excuses I made for Lejun
心の中でおまえのために
in my heart,
言い訳を探しても
the friendship between us
俺とおまえの絆は
still came to an abrupt end.
あっけなく途切れてしまった
Because
なぜなら
that was my dearest mother.
あの方は 私が最も敬愛する母上でした
She always hoped
母上はずっと望んでおられました
I could become a true emperor,
私が真の帝王となることを
free from anyone's constraints.
誰にも束縛されぬよう
She was worried I'd become too dependent on Xiao Wuyi,
私が無衣に依存しすぎることを心配し
and that
私があなたを前にして
I'd let my guard down because of you.
心が揺らぐことも案じていました
Through this deadly gambit,
母上はこの必死の策で
she fulfilled the plan Wuyi and I had devised,
私と無衣の計画を成就させ
yet she also severed all ties
そして私たちの絆を
between us once and for all.
完全に断ち切ったのです
"Five days from now, when the north wind rises,
五日後 北風が吹く時
meet at Dingfeng Slope."
定風坂
This was found on the sole of Li Lejun's shoe.
これは李楽君様の靴裏から見つかりました
It seems the day for the decisive battle
どうやら決戦の日が
has finally come.
ついに来たようだな
The new caltrop fireball is ready.
新しい火蒺藜が完成した
It's completely different from the previous version.
以前のものとは全くの別物だ
I'll take you to see it.
案内する
I'll go make the record.
私は記録を
Okay.
よし
This is called "stone fat,"
これは石脂
also known as "weishui."
またの名を洧水という
Stone fat oil deposits are different from lard or tallow.
石脂は豚や牛の油とは違い
They form alongside mineral deposits.
鉱床と共に産出される
They are flammable but inedible,
燃えるが食用にはならん
and even water cannot extinguish them.
水では消せず
They can stretch for thousands of miles
千里に広がり
and burn without end.
燃え尽きることがない
Even water can't extinguish them?
水でも消せぬとは
Then with this substance,
これさえあれば
we'll surely be invincible.
百戦百勝だな
I once promised Wuyi
以前 無衣に約束した
that I'd create the caltrop fireball before the Northern Expedition.
北伐の前に火蒺藜を完成させると
Though he's not here today and cannot see it,
今日あいつはいないし 見ることもできんが
I haven't failed in my mission.
だが使命は果たした
I have to go now.
もう行くわ
But don't worry.
でも安心して
Cui Shao'an is overseeing the production of the caltrop fireball.
火蒺藜は崔少安殿が監造するから
Are you going to find Wuyi?
無衣殿を捜しに
This battle could result in a great victory
この戦は北府にとって
for the Beifu Army,
大鄴にとっても あなたにとっても
for Ye, and for you.
大勝利を収める好機です
But for Xiao Wuyi,
だが蕭無衣にとっては
defeat is certain.
惨敗は必至だ
He had already resolved to die,
彼はもとより死を覚悟している
and now, the two-month deadline is nearly up,
二か月の期限も迫り
and the miraculous doctor's medicine won't last much longer.
神医の薬も長くはもたない
I won't let him die.
死なせはしない
I'm going to find him.
捜しに行くわ
I'll definitely bring him back alive.
必ず生きて連れ戻す
The loyalty to stand through life and death together—
生死を共にする義理か
that's the Xie Jiayu I know.
謝嘉魚さんらしい
Go on.
行くがいい
You're not stopping me?
止めないの
I tried.
止めたさ
But I couldn't.
だが止められん
Take care.
ご無事で
You take care too.
あなたも
Do you really have to go to the Northern Border?
どうしても北境へ
I built the Beifu Army all by myself,
北府軍は私が築いた
and they once answered only to my command.
私一人の命のみを聴く
Three years have passed since the reforms. The military system may have changed,
改制して三年 軍制は改まったが
but the loyalty of the soldiers has not.
だが軍心は変わらぬ
Yizhi.
易之
The tragedy of the An and Lu families must never happen again.
安陸二氏の悲劇を繰り返してはならぬ
The army's loyalty should not lie with one man,
軍心は一人にあらず
but with the people.
万民にある
No matter who becomes the commander of
北府軍の統帥が
the Beifu Army,
誰になろうと
and even without me, Xiao Wuyi,
この蕭無衣がいなくとも
the Beifu Army must know
北府軍は知らねばならぬ
that they are fighting for Ye.
自らが大鄴のために戦うのだと
So you don't plan to come back?
では もう戻らないつもり
Will we ever see each other again?
また会える
I hope that, in the final days of my life,
命の最後に
I can pave the way for the Northern Expedition.
北伐への道を開きたい
Was this your plan from the very beginning?
最初から こうするつもりだったの
What about Xie Jiayu then?
では謝嘉魚は
Tell Xiao Wuyi that,
蕭無衣に伝えよ
as he wished,
望みどおり
the next time we meet, it will be as emperor and subject.
次に会う時は君臣だと
Got it, Mao.
分かった 阿茂
Goodbye, Yaoyao.
さらばだ 夭夭
Your Highness Prince Qi,
岐王殿下
I hereby take my leave.
これにて失礼いたします
Goodbye,
さらばだ
Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚
Bring all the military reports and memorials here.
軍報と奏状を全て持ってまいれ
I won't get married.
嫁いだりしない
I just want to stay by your side, Mao.
兄上のそばにいるわ
I have the best older brother in the entire world.
私には天下一の兄上がいるもの
Mao.
兄上
I will protect you, no matter what.
私が必ずお守りします
We've just received a battle report.
たった今 戦報が届きました
Last night, scouts detected a sudden fire
一昨夜 北府の陣営から
breaking out at the Beifu Army Camp.
突然 火の手が上がったと
Li Mao's army immediately broke camp
李茂の大軍は直ちに陣を引き
and marched westward, bypassing the Jing River.
涇水を迂回し西へ向かったと
He's going to Dingfeng Slope.
狙いは定風坂だ
Dingfeng Slope?
定風坂
Li Mao must be heading there,
李茂は必ずそこへ行く
because Dingfeng Slope holds a secret that has never been revealed to outsiders.
定風坂には人に知られざる秘密があるからだ
What secret?
秘密とは
To the south of Dingfeng Slope
定風坂の南には
are 2 iron mines marked by the Phoenix Heart Tokens.
雀骨令が示す鉄鉱が二つある
If he holds Dingfeng Slope
定風坂さえ守れば
and establishes a Directorate of Military Equipment there,
ここに軍械監を建て
using it as a base
砦とし
to train troops, forge weapons,
兵を養い武具を鋳造
store grain, and raise livestock,
兵糧を備蓄し牧畜を行えば
not only will the capture of the Capital be just a matter of time,
上京も目前となるばかりか
but he'll also no longer have to rely on the aristocratic clans for supplies.
今後は名家の補給に頼らずに済む
Your Highness.
殿下
There's a woman outside
外に女子が参っております
claiming to be Xiao Wuyi's consort.
蕭無衣の世子妃を名乗っております
Let me go.
離して
I just told you,
さっきも言ったでしょ
I am Xiao Wuyi's consort.
私は蕭無衣の世子妃よ
If you don't believe me,
信じられないなら
just call him out and ask him yourself.
本人を呼んで聞けばいいじゃない
Xiao Wuyi, I'm here!
蕭無衣 ここにいるわ
Xiao Wuyi...
蕭無衣
Look at him.
ほら あの人よ
Just let me go.
離してちょうだい
You... Tell him to let me go.
あなた 彼に離させなさい
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
What are you doing here?
何しに来た
I'm here to share life and death with you.
生死を共にするためよ
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
I had to set the Beifu Army Camp
北府の陣営に
on fire just to escape.
火を放って逃げてきたのよ
And this is how you greet me?
その態度は何なの
All those days I spent crying for you were for nothing then.
あなたのために泣き続けたのに
Xie Jiayu, long time no see.
謝嘉魚さん ご無事でしたか
It seems you are truly devoted
世子様には
to Young Lord Xiao.
実に一途なようだな
Let her in.
中へ通せ
Yes!
はっ
The food is ready. Please enjoy.
お食事の用意ができました どうぞ
Xiao Wuyi...
蕭無衣
Now that you've escaped Li Mao's control,
もう李茂の支配から逃れたのだから
you could go anywhere you wish.
好きに行けばいいものを
Why come running here and throw yourself into danger?
なぜ わざわざ罠にはまりに来た
Are you crazy?
馬鹿か
Don't you know
分かっているのか
that once you enter this place,
一度ここに足を踏み入れたら
leaving will be nearly impossible?
抜け出すのは困難だぞ
How many times do I have to tell you?
何度言えば分かる
I'm here to share life and death with you.
生死を共にするために来たの
Understood?
分かった？
But
でも
if you're bothered by the fact that Li Mao forced me to marry him,
李茂に無理やり嫁がされたのを気にしてるなら
then I'll leave right now.
今すぐ出ていく
What nonsense are you talking about?
何を馬鹿なことを
Then why haven't you smiled at me even once?
なのに なぜ笑ってもくれないんだ
I've already resolved to die.
私はもう死を覚悟している
My reputation out there is in tatters.
世間での評判も地に落ちた
Why should I drag you down
なぜ君をそばに置いてまで
to suffer alongside me?
苦労をさせねばならん
Didn't we promise each other long ago that
昔 約束したでしょう
whether you achieve glory and fame
あなたが成功を収めても
or are reviled by the masses,
世に罵られても
I will always be by your side?
そばにいると
I, Xie Jiayu, stand by my word.
私 謝嘉魚は有言実行よ
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
As husband and wife, our fates are bound together.
夫婦は一心同体よ
All I want is for you to live.
君に生きていてほしい
Even if everyone abandons me,
たとえ皆に裏切られても
as long as you're by my side,
君がそばにいてくれれば
I, Xiao Wuyi, won't have lived this life in vain.
私 蕭無衣の人生も無駄ではない
Once I've wiped out Li Mao's army,
李茂の大軍を殲滅したら
I'll come find you.
君を迎えに行く
The weapon I promised you—
君と約束した武器は
I've successfully made it.
もうできている
Your Highness.
殿下
Xiao Wuyi and Xie Jiayu
蕭無衣と謝嘉魚は
have been doing nothing but
一日中 飲み食いしており
eating and drinking all day.
何の動きもありませぬ
What do you make of this, Imperial Envoy
勅使殿は いかがお考えですかな
Do you think Young Lord Xiao's consort
世子妃が来たのは
really just came here
本当に蕭無衣と
to share life and death with Xiao Wuyi?
生死を共にするためだけでしょうか
I've heard a saying among common folk,
わしが聞くところ 民間ではこう申します
"Husband and wife are like birds of a feather.
“夫婦はもとより同じ林の鳥
But when disaster strikes, they fly their separate ways."
災い来れば各々飛び去る”と
Your Highness surely doesn't really believe
殿下は まさか
there's anyone in this world who'd die for love, do you?
この世に愛のために死ぬ者がいるなどと お思いではありますまいな
I certainly don't believe it.
余も信じてはいない
But that Xie Jiayu is truly different.
だが この謝嘉魚は別だ
Back in Jiankang,
かつて剣慷にいた頃
Xiao Wuyi was deeply in love with her,
蕭無衣は彼女に惚れ込み
yet she was childhood sweethearts with Li Mao.
彼女は李茂と幼なじみであった
Between Xiao Wuyi and Li Mao,
蕭無衣と李茂の間で
Li Lejun's death was merely the last straw.
李楽君の死が最後の引き金となったが
The one who truly drove those two apart
真に兄弟を争わせたのは
was Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚なのだ
Since Xiao Wuyi and Xie Jiayu
蕭無衣と謝嘉魚の絆が
share such a deep bond,
それほど深いのであれば
doesn't that mean we've got
我々は蕭無衣の弱みを
even more leverage against Xiao Wuyi now?
また一つ握ったも同然
His Majesty means...
陛下のお考えは
This is a rare opportunity.
これは またとない好機だ
Very well. As His Majesty commands,
よし 陛下の仰せのとおり
even if the mines at Dingfeng Slope
定風坂の鉱床が
turn out to be a colossal trap,
たとえ巨大な罠だとしても
we shall still brave it.
我らも正面から挑んでやろう
Beat the drums and muster the troops!
太鼓を鳴らし 兵を招集せよ
Understood!
はっ
Your Highness, please don't go any further.
世子 これ以上はなりませぬ
Got it.
分かっている
You all head back first.
お前たちは先に戻れ
What?
何です
Are Heir's words no longer enough to command you?
世子の言葉が聞こえなかったのですか
His Highness said
あなたたちの殿下は仰せでしたね
that Heir's an important guest here,
世子は上客であると
yet you keep watching us every day.
それを毎日監視するとは
Do you intend to eavesdrop on our private affairs as well?
夫婦の閨事まで聞く気ですの
Step back.
下がれ
The Eagle King probably thought
鷹王はきっと
you came here to gather information.
探りに来たとでも思ったでしょう
Who would have thought
まさか
you really came to join me in death?
本当に私と死ぬために来たとは
So, are you saying
では
I shouldn't have come?
私が来たのは間違いだったと
I didn't mean that.
間違ってない
Tell me the truth—
正直に言って
were you happy to see me?
私が来てうれしい
I was.
うれしい
I was so happy.
すごくうれしい
Then do you know how upset I was
では 私が手紙を読んだ時
when I saw your letter?
どれだけ不機嫌だったか分かる
Xiao Wuyi, if you ever do something like this again,
蕭無衣 次にまた同じことをしたら
I will absolutely not forgive you.
絶対に許さないから
Or
いっそ
you can just go live with Li Mao.
李茂と一緒になればいい
No, that's not right either. Li Mao said
いや 違うわ 李茂は言ってた
the next time you met,
次に会う時は
as you wished,
望みどおり
it'd be as emperor and subject.
ただの君臣だと
The coroner has done the autopsy.
検視役が検死を終えました
Before Lejun died,
楽君は死ぬ前に
she had already taken poison.
すでに毒を飲んでいたそうです
You never meant to shoot that arrow.
あの矢は本意ではなかった
Even if Li Lejun had taken poison
たとえ李楽君が毒を飲んでいたとしても
and was destined to die,
彼女は逝く運命だった
Lejun was still his sister.
だが楽君は やはり彼の妹だ
In the end, what that arrow
最後のあの矢が
shot through was the youthful friendship
射抜いたのは蕭無衣と李茂の
between Xiao Wuyi and Li Mao.
少年の頃の友情だ
Then on the battlefield,
では戦場では
you two...
お二人とも
No matter how my relationship with Yizhi
私と易之の関係が
changes,
どう変わろうと
when it comes to Southern Ye
南鄴のため
and the affairs of the court,
朝廷のため
we'll always share the same aspirations.
我々には常に同じ志がある
This is something he'll never change.
その点だけは 彼は決して変わらない
Now that so many people have sacrificed,
今となっては これほど多くの者が犠牲になった
no matter how hard the road ahead is,
この道がどれだけ険しくとも
we must persevere and keep moving forward.
歩み続けねばならない
Did Lejun
楽君は
leave any final words?
何か言い残しては
If you ever have the chance,
機会があれば
please deliver this message to Jiayu for me:
嘉魚に伝えてほしい
I have never done anything
楽君はこの生涯で
in my life that I regret.
後悔したことはないと
Be it resentment or hatred,
恨みも憎しみも
I've accepted it all willingly.
すべて甘んじて受け入れると
As I reach the end of my journey,
道の終わりに
my only regret is
ただ心残りなのは
that I won't be able to
大鄴の山川湖海を
view the beautiful landscapes of Ye with her.
彼女と共に見て回れないことだと
Why are you sighing?
何をため息ついてるの
Nothing.
別に
I just hope when we return to Jiankang,
ただ 剣慷に戻った時に
we'll still make it in time for the Thousand Lantern Festival.
また千灯会に間に合えばと
The journey of life is like sailing on a boat.
人生とは舟旅のようなもの
The passengers come and go,
乗る者は来たり去ったりする
and some people
そしてある者は
are destined to accompany you only for a part of the journey.
道の途中までしか共に歩めぬ運命なのだ
When their time comes, they will leave.
時が来れば去っていく
We must learn to let go.
諦めることも学ばねば
That may be true,
理屈ではそうだが
but I don't want to hear
でも聞きたくない
any words of ill omen.
縁起でもない話は
Not today,
今日も聞かない
not tomorrow.
明日も聞かない
Xiao Wuyi, hold out your hand.
蕭無衣 手を出して
What is this?
これは何
This is a life-saving pill
これは私が名医先生に
I begged the miraculous doctor to make.
頼んでもらった命拾いの薬よ
Keep it safe.
ちゃんと持っていて
Why are there so many people?
なぜこんなに人が
Your Highness.
殿下
What's this supposed to mean?
どういうことだ
Throughout history,
古来より
whenever generals went off to war,
将帥が出征する際は
their family members were often held as hostages.
家族を人質に取るもの
Li Lejun took this poison as well.
この毒は李楽君も飲んだ
As long as we win,
我々が勝利さえすれば
Young Lord Xiao, your consort and the people of Southern Ye
世子妃と南鄴の民は
will surely be safe and sound.
必ずやご無事だ
Your Highness, this place is surrounded by mountains on all sides,
殿下 この地は四方を山に囲まれ
with only a small road leading out to the northeast.
あるのは北東の小道のみです
If the Beifu Army are to block this road,
北府軍にこの道を断たれては
we'll be trapped here with no escape.
ここは死地となります
Although this map is authentic,
この地図は本物ですが
I fear Young Lord Xiao may have ulterior motives.
蕭世子には別の狙いがあるかと
Pass my order:
伝えよ
Act as usual.
平常どおりに
Lure the enemy in!
敵を誘い込め
Roger that!
はっ
It seems Your Highness has never trusted me.
殿下は一度も私を信じておられなかったのですね
Was my acting really that bad?
私の芝居はそれほど下手でしたか
Your acting was excellent, Young Lord Xiao.
世子の芝居は見事だった
It's just a pity I don't care for plays.
だが余は芝居が嫌いでな
If you told me you were plotting a rebellion, I'd believe it.
世子が謀反を企てたとあらば信じよう
But that you'd defect to Northern Qin?
だが北秦に寝返るなど
No matter how well your acting was,
いかに見事な芝居でも
I'd never believe it.
余は信じぬ
My men have all arrived.
兵は揃った
Today is the day
今日こそ
that Beifu meets its end!
北府の最期だ
They are all still alive?
彼らは死んでいない
Even if the Xiao family were to die,
蕭家の者は
they'd only die on the battlefield.
戦場でしか死なぬ
How could they possibly die because of your schemes and treachery?
貴様の罠で死ぬものか
So it was all fake from the very beginning?
では 最初からすべて偽りだったのだな
Warriors of Beifu!
北府軍の兵よ
Charge!
かかれ
Kill!
討て
Wuyi, catch this!
無衣 受け取れ
Move, move. Faster.
急げ
Faster!
早く
Move.
行け
Hurry up!
急げ
Hurry!
早くしろ
Move faster!
さあ
Come on!
早く行け
Faster!
急げ
What are you dawdling for?
ぐずぐずするな
Promise me
約束して
you'll take good care of yourself
ちゃんと生きると
and wait for me to come back.
戻るまで待ってて
Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣
You liar!
この嘘つき
Move, move.
行け
Faster!
急げ
Move faster!
さっさとしろ
Move.
行け
Grandma!
ばあさん
What are you doing?
何してる
Hurry up.
早くしろ
Stop hitting him!
やめろ
Get up!
立て
My kid...
坊や
What are you looking at? Get to work!
見てないで 働け
Killing is for the sake of saving lives.
人を殺すのは人を救うため
Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚さん
You're not left with nothing.
あなたは手ぶらではない
The Northern Qin people see us Ye people as nothing more than pigs and sheep
北秦の者共は我ら鄴人を家畜同然に扱っている
to be slaughtered. Rather than waiting here to die
ここで死を待つよりは
and be slaughtered,
なすがままに殺されるくらいなら
why not take up your weapons
その手に武器を取り
and fight them?
奴らと戦おう
They are no different from us.
奴らも我々と同じ
They are also made of flesh and blood.
血の通った人間だ
They too will die and feel fear.
同じく死を恐れる
Don't you
皆
want to go home?
故郷へ帰りたくないのか
We all will die sooner or later.
遅かれ早かれ死ぬ身だ
At worst, we die together!
ならば共に死のう
No one is born a coward.
人は生まれつき臆病なわけではない
It's just when they become accustomed to bowing their heads,
ただ頭を下げることに慣れると
courage and determination
勇気と決意は
must be shown to them by someone—
誰かが命と
with their life and blood.
血をもって示さねばならぬものだ
You came just in time.
ちょうどいいところに来たな
Let's get this over with quickly
短期決戦で
and go save Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣を救うぞ
He's about to take the Eagle King down with him.
鷹王と相打ちする気だ
Father.
父上
Xiao Wuyi, you've lost.
蕭無衣 お前の負けだ
Today, Dingfeng Slope
今日の定風坡が
will be the graveyard for both you and the Beifu Army!
貴様と北府軍の墓場となる
Who wins and who loses,
誰が勝ち 誰が負けるか
who lives and who dies—
誰が生き 誰が死ぬか
it still remains to be seen.
まだ分からぬさ
His Majesty's army has arrived!
陛下の大軍が到着したぞ
Defend!
守れ
Retreat!
退け
Attack!
殺せ
Eagle King.
鷹王
How could you run away?
なぜ逃げる
This battle has just begun.
この戦は始まったばかりだ
So you threw yourself into this
まさか 我が身を投じたのは
not for me,
私のためではなく
but for...
…
Think about it. Prince Qi wouldn't let me take all the military credit.
岐王が手柄を独占させぬとでも
Then would your young emperor
ならば そちらの若造の皇帝が
spare a powerful minister like you?
貴様のような権臣を見逃すと思うか
Now that we've both suffered heavy losses,
我らが共倒れになった今
he wants to reap the spoils.
漁夫の利を得るつもりか
But little does he know
だが自分が
that he's the real prey in this game.
本当の獲物だとは知るまい
Load!
火薬を込め
Prime!
弾を込め
Fire!
点火
So this is the true main force of the Beifu Army.
これこそが北府軍の真の主力だ
The Beifu Army
北府軍は
has burned and cut off all the escape routes from Dingfeng Slope!
定風坡から逃れる道をすべて焼き払った
Xiao Wuyi saw that I was at odds with His Majesty,
蕭無衣は私と陛下の不仲を見抜き
so he deliberately put himself into this fray,
我が身をおとりに
all to lure His Majesty into taking action so he could wipe out the main force
陛下を誘き出し
of our Northern Qin Army here at Dingfeng Slope.
定風坡で我が大秦の主力を全滅させるためだ
He and his father
蕭家の親子は
never intended to return alive.
生きて帰るつもりなど毛頭なかったのだ
Even if I die today,
今日ここで死ぬとしても
I'll personally finish you off!
この手で貴様を殺す
Yao!
兄さん
Father!
父上
-Father! -Yao, let's go!
父上 兄さん 逃げて
I won't leave.
行かぬ
Don't look back.
振り返るな
Go!
行け
Father!
父上
Wuyi, I can agree to your plan,
無衣 そなたの策には同意しよう
but you need to agree to one condition:
だが条件が１つある
you must stay alive.
生きてほしい
Those with ambition cling to life;
志ある者は生に執着し
those who die for their cause seek death.
道に殉じる者は死を求める
Xiao Wuyi, cling to life for me from now on,
蕭無衣 今後は私のために生を貪ってくれ
will you?
よいな
I'm sorry, Yaoyao.
すまない 夭夭
Fire!
放て
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
You lunatic!
この狂人が
As Crown Prince Wenxi,
文熹太子でありながら
do you really have no regard for your own life?
己の命さえ惜しくないのか
Someone like you
貴様のような者には
will never understand what I've been fighting for in this life.
私が生涯を懸けて戦う理由など永遠に分かるまい